# JAMES BOWKETT

## http://github.com/jbowkett • 07967 156 887 • https://linkedin.com/in/jamesbowkett

I am a professional, hands-on Technical Lead and Architect with almost 20 years software development experience predominantly using Java in various finance-related enterprise environments. I am a strong advocate of TDD and BDD practices employing SOLID design to continuously deliver clean code.

## **EMPLOYMENT HISTORY**

# January 2015 - Present • Senior Principal Consultant, Head of Engineering, Digital Consulting • Excelian, London

Excelian is the financial services line of business for Luxoft. The Digital Consulting Practice specialise in delivering large outsourced projects in technologies such as: UI/UX, AI/ML, cloud/devops and big/fast data. I have held several roles during my tenure from Blockchain Lead to Head of Engineering.

- Technical Team Lead responsible for all parts of the technical delivery (design, architecture, mentoring and implementation) for a 60-person team (across 3 geographies) for a European investment bank's trade data lake to underpin the bank's data strategy and Mifid II reporting. The architecture made use of microservices, Kafka and continuous delivery.
- Blockchain Lead for financial services, responsible for the technical direction of the team in St. Petersburg while running workshops and pre-sales engagements with many financial services institutions.
- Lead Architect for a risk architecture review for a British investment bank.
- Senior Developer for a fixed income low latency pricing platform incorporating Fixed income market data from Bloomberg and Reutersusing Ion and 29 West.
- Technical Team Lead for a risk reporting project for a European investment bank.
- Core committer to Mache an open source big data near-side cache written in Java.
- Architected and presented solutions for new projects to various capital markets clients, on subjects ranging from data lakes to microservices.
- Presented at Java and blockchain conferences to audiences of around 100 people.
- Technical Mentor for Hyperledger Fabric at the Hack the Valley blockchain hackathon in Zug, Switzerland.
- Leader for the development community of practice, organising fortnightly meetups of events and presentations to improve the skills and levels of engagement of the other consultants.
- Direct line manager to 10+ consultants.
- Consistently rated "Outstanding" or "Excellent" in all mid and full-year reviews.

## September 2014 - December 2014 • Proton Consultant • Prosperity Capital Management, London

Prosperity Capital manage in excess of 4bn USD in assets. Following the demise of Lyagushka I was responsible for an extended period of handover for the trade lifecycle platform. This involved training and deep-dives into all areas of the existing codebase to enable a successful transition to the new team.

## October 2012 - September 2014 • Lead Developer • Lyagushka, London

Lyagushka provided the full trade lifecycle platform incorporating complex business rules and asset allocation for Prosperity Capital. The platform was developed using MongoDB, Mysql and Ruby on Rails employing highly agile

methodologies for planning (morning standups, planning poker, Kanban boards) and development (TDD, BDD and pair programming).

- Architected, designed, implemented and led the development of various components including stock movements, SWIFT and fund level accounting.
- Part of the management team responsible for the orderly wind down of the company, including demos to clients and investors.
- Team Lead to an external consultancy.
- Oversaw and maintained a high level of automation, leading to the capability to go from bug report to bugfix to production in under 1 hour.
- Introduced various tooling and techniques such as constructor injection, Trello, Harvest.

#### April 2007 - September 2012 • Software Engineer • Cygna Negra Capital Management, London

Cygna Negra was a long-short hedge fund trading US equities. Prior to its incorporation, I was approached by the CEO to be responsible for all software engineering, systems setup and administration.

Architected and implemented the following major pieces of infrastructure:

- Configurable ETL pipeline for USPTO grants, applications, reassignments, trademarks and SEC filings.
- Database of company family tree taking data from various sources such as Hoovers, S&P and Google.
- Company research augmented Web UI for team of 10 researchers.
- Workflow server for allocation of work to researchers.
- Discrepancy and reconciliation tool for researcher output.
- Text cleaning libraries for automatic matching of patent assignees with various company family tree databases.
- · Autonomous web crawlers for harvesting company information from known public sites.
- Web applications for visualising company family tree data, analytics, patent portfolio analytics.
- Custom obfuscation and signing maven Mojo to integrate with webstart jar files.
- · Gridgain implementation for assignee matching.

## May 2006 - April 2007 • Senior Software Engineer • Iris Financial Solutions, London

Iris Financial supplied real-time Java FX pricing engines to major investment banks. I was responsible for delivering low latency code to clients such as Citigroup and JP Morgan.

• Implemented modules for real time FX Spot pricing engine, including stale fixing notifications, JMX management and config visualisation.

## June 2005 - May 2006 • Associate Analyst Programmer • JP Morgan Asset Management, London

JP Morgan AM provide asset management services to both retail and institutional investors. As part of the reporting team, I was responsible for internal development and seconded into the build manager role leading to 20 successful releases following a prolonged period of instability.

- Managed external vendor for a data maintenance platform from documenting initial requirements through to implementation.
- Developed various server-side, data management command line Java tools.

## June 2000 - June 2005 • Senior Software Engineer • Searchspace, London (acquired by Nice Actimize)

Searchspace provided anti-money laundering and fraud detection products to tier-1 retail banks in the UK and US. Following several promotions after starting as an intern, I was ultimately responsible for the technical leadership of the core platform team and 3 new anti-fraud products.

- Technical lead for several teams : 3 new anti-fraud sentinel products, the core IEF team and a leading Canadian retail Bank.
- Developed IEF server components for major deployments, including 32-bit memory caching in Java 1.3.
- Mentored junior developers/interviewed new hires.

## **EDUCATION / QUALIFICATIONS**

- 2014 Mongo University Mongo 101
- 2004 British Computer Society MBCS
- 1997-2000 University of Sussex 2:1 (Hons) BSc Computer Science
- 1995-1997 Westcliff High School For Boys Sixth Form 4 A-levels
- 1995-1996 Southend Adult Education Community College A-level in Computer Science
- Summer 1995 SEETEC NVQ Level 2 diploma in Information Technology
- 1990-1995 Westcliff High School for Boys 10 GCSEs
- 1982-1990 College Saint Pierre Preparatory School